Ever since I was a child,
I felt like there were walls up.
子どものころから　壁があるように感じていた
"1st Year"
They would...
それは
私を取り囲み　自由に行動することを阻む…
...hem me in and prevent me
from doing whatever I wanted.
見えない… 高い壁
High, unseen walls.
その壁を乗り越えたくて
I wanted to climb over those walls...
so I began living on my own.
一人暮らしを始めた
Then, after that...
そして… 次は
Long time.
久しぶり
いらっしゃい　さっ　入って
Welcome. Come on in.
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
Be my guest.
どうぞ
適当に座って　今お茶いれるから
Have a seat anywhere.
I'll make us some tea.
I'd rather have water instead of tea.
お茶より水がいい
You got it.
了解
はい
Here.
ありがとう
Thanks.
晩ごはん何がいい？
What would you like for supper?
What do I even have, anyway?
何があったかな…
今日こっちに帰ってきたばかりで　ロクなものがない…
I just got back here today,
so there isn't much of--
I bought us something.
買ってきてる
えっ？
Huh?
今作るから　台所貸して
I'll make it now.
Let me use your kitchen.
何作ってくれるの？
What are you making for us?
お好み焼き
Okonomiyaki. Unless you don't like it.
苦手じゃないなら
Hmm! I love okonomiyaki!
お好み焼き　大好きよん
できた　食べよう
They're done. Let's eat.
う～ん　いただきま～す
Mm, thank you for this food!
いただきます
Thank you for this food.
ん～うまい！
Mm, it's good!
ねっ　バイトは？どうだった？
So, did that job of yours go all right?
Mm-hmm. It went smoothly. How about you?
うん　滞りなく
そっちは？
んっ？
Hmm?
夏休み　どこに行っていたの？
Where did you go for summer vacation?
前に言ったでしょう
I told you before, didn't I?
近くて…遠い場所
Somewhere close... yet far away.
"Super Cub Episode 5"
"Reiko's Summer"
オーライ　オーライ　オーライ！
Back it up, back it up,
back it up... Stop!
ストーップ！
よ～し　運べ！
Okay, start loading!
うぃ～っす！
--Right.
Here it comes...
...three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, ten...
3　4　5　6　7　8　9　10…
--The amount of supplies
is increasing, huh?
物資の量　増えてきますね
店長　定数どおりです
--Chief, the count is right.
--The amount of supplies
is increasing, huh?
あぁ
Okay.
じゃあ　走路確認に行ってきます
Well, I'm going to go check the trail.
There's still plenty of time,
so don't rush it.
まだ時間あるから　ゆっくり行っといで
Drive safely.
ご安全に
はい　ご安全に
Right. I'll drive safely.
よし
Okay...
チクショウ！
Damn it!
高校 2 年の夏
The summer of my second
year in high school,
私はスーパーカブで　富士山を登っていた
I climbed Mt. Fuji on my Super Cub.
Nothing out of the ordinary on the trail.
走路　異常ありませんでした
あぁ　ご苦労さま
Okay, good job.
よ～し　行くぞ～
All right, let's go!
--Right.
うぃ～っす！
"Mt. Fuji Subashiri Trail Station 5"
"Mountain Hut Kikuya"
Why are you doing this?
なんでこんなことするんだ？
興味を持ったのは　ある二輪冒険家の本を読んだから
I first became interested when I read
a book by a biker adventurist.
あぁ　昔はバイクで富士山登るなんて　よくやってたらしいな
Yeah, apparently, they used to climb
Mt. Fuji on motorbikes a lot back then.
今はもうできないんですか？
Can you not do it anymore?
With environmental regulations
and mountain climbing rules,
環境規制とか　登山マナーとか　昔と比べて厳しいからね
things are a lot more strict
now compared to before.
まぁ　しかたねえよな
Yeah, there's not much you can do.
"Due to the treacherous
debris and steep slope,
険しいガレキの急斜面は　高性能なオフロードバイクしか登れない…
only a high-performance off-road
bike can make the climb."
I guess it's out of the question.
さすがに無理か…
"Super Cub off-road custom"
CT110 ハンターカブ
A CT110 Hunter Cub...
そっか…
That's it. I don't need to tweak Super
Cub parts; I could just use these.
スーパーカブ用のチューニングパーツじゃなくて　こっちを使えば…
よし
There.
でも　バイクができても
Still, even if I have the bike to do it,
富士山を登る許可が下りるわけじゃない
that doesn't mean I'm going to
get permission to climb Mt. Fuji.
うちでバイトしてる間は　麓のアパートに泊まり込んでもらうけど
While you're working for us,
you'll have to stay at an apartment
at the foot of the mountain.
大丈夫です
That's fine.
登山経験は？
Any mountain climbing experience?
ありません
No, sir.
Is that a requirement?
ないといけませんか？
いや　別に
No, not really. So, as for why
you want to work here...
で…
志望動機だけど…
"I want to climb Mt. Fuji
on my motorbike."
Right, it's just as I've written there.
はい　そこに書いたとおりです
私は　富士山をバイクで登りたいんです
I want to climb Mt. Fuji on my motorbike.
Loading work starts tomorrow morning at 4.
荷積みの仕事は明日の朝 4 時から
Also, I've decided to have
you do the trail checks.
それと　走路の確認もしてもらうことにしたから
Trail checks?
走路の確認？
You have to check the weather
and surface conditions
キャタピラ車が出発する前に　天候や路面の状態をチェックしてもらう
before the Caterpillar heads out.
ソイツでな
On that.
Huh?
えっ
まぁ　チェックは六合目まででいいんだが
And you only really have
to check up to Station 6,
必要なら　もっと上まで登ってもらってもかまわないから
but if it's necessary, I won't mind
if you go up higher than that.
Right! Thank you very much!
はい！ありがとうございます！
なんでこんなことするんだ？
Why are you doing this?
私は知りたいだけです
I just want to know...
自分があれを…乗り越えられる人間か
...if I'm the kind of person who can
overcome something like that.
クッソ…
Damn...
Nothing out of the ordinary on the trail.
走路　異常ありませんでした
あぁ
Okay.
Altitude sickness.
高山病だな
ありがとう…ございます
Thank you very much.
Sip it. Don't gulp it all down at once.
少しずつ　一気に飲んじゃだめだから
Right.
はい
"Summiting Everest"
Damn it...
チクショウ…
Damn it...! Damn it...!
チクショウ！
Damn it, damn it, damn it...!
チクショウ　チクショウ　チクショウ！
Damn it!
チックショーッ！
チク… ショウ…
Damn... it...
山に体を立てちゃいけない
You can't stand yourself
up to the mountain.
You have to bring yourself alongside it.
体を沿わせるんだ
えっ…
Bring myself... alongside?
山に…体を？
Even in the summer, Mt. Fuji has a slight
blanket of snow at its summit.
山頂に　かすかな雪化粧が残る夏の富士
きれいな山だと思った
I thought it was such a pretty mountain.
I want to see it up close.
もっと近くで見てみよう
もっと高い場所から見下ろせば　更にきれいに違いない
No doubt if you look down on it
from somewhere even higher,
it looks even prettier.
ここ数日の連敗で　笑顔すら忘れていた
After my string of failures
these last few days,
I'd even forgotten how to smile.
I was climbing Mt. Fuji on my Cub.
カブで富士山を登る
Why, when I was doing something this fun,
こんなに楽しいことをするのに
did it feel like I was being made to
suffer by some despicable enemy?
なんで私は　憎むべき敵に苦しめられているような気分になっていたんだろう
I'm off to go check the trail.
走路確認　行ってきます
Drive safely.
ご安全に
There's nothing wrong with the suspension.
サスペンションは問題ない
The frame is buckling
a tiny bit, but it's fine.
フレームは少しよじれるけど　大丈夫
The engine's electricals
and fuel are on the money.
エンジンも電装も燃料もよし
あとは… 私自身！
All that leaves is me!
Damn...
クッソー！
山に体を立てちゃいけない　体を沿わせるんだ
You can't stand yourself
up to the mountain.
You have to bring yourself alongside it.
あれは力を抜いて　山に身を委ねろって意味じゃなくて
That doesn't mean that you go limp
and give yourself over to the mountain;
全力で身を伏せ　踏ん張るしかないってこと！
you have to hold yourself down
and fight as hard as you can!
But this is tough, all right.
でも　やっぱりきつい
いける！まだいける！
You can do it! You can keep going!
--This is crazy! I want to stop!
--I want to climb! I want to go higher!
ムチャだ　もうやめたい
登りたい　もっと高く！
--Damn it!
--I want to climb! I want to go higher!
チクショウ！
I can't give up now!
あきらめるわけにはいかない！
また来年　挑戦する
--I can always try again next year.
--You dummy! Keep on running!
バーカ！
走れ！走れ！走れ！
A Super Cub. A used one.
スーパーカブ　中古の
Oh, a Cub? That's more of a scooter
than a motorbike, isn't it?
なんだよ　カブかよ～
バイクってか原付じゃん　それ
You ride a Cub?
あなたはカブに乗っているの？
Sitting on my Cub like this,
こうやってカブに乗っていると
たとえ止まっていても
it feels like I can go anywhere
I like, as far away as I like,
自分がどこにでも　どこまでも行けるっていう気分を感じられるのよ
even when I'm standing still.
まだ遠くに行ったこと…ないから
I haven't gone all that far away, so...
どこにでも行けるわよ
You can go anywhere you want to.
I mean, you've got a Cub!
だってカブだもん
Somewhere close, yet far away.
近くて…遠い場所
Be careful, okay?
気をつけてね
Yeah.
えぇ
I don't have enough oxygen...
or hydration... But...
酸素が足りない… 水分も
でも…
...I told her... that she
could go anywhere...
私　あの子に言ったんだ　「どこにでも行ける」って
And after telling her that,
I can't very well stop here!
自分で言っといて
止まるわけにはいかない！
Damn it!
チクショーッ！
えぇ　終わりました
Yeah, I'm finished.
Could I ask you to pick me up on
your way down from the summit?
頂上輸送の帰りに　拾っていただけますか？
んっ
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
You didn't get all the way to the top?
上までは行けなかったか
Still, I don't feel too bad.
でも… 悪くない気分です
That's silly.
バカみたい
Yeah, you're right about that.
I was wondering, myself,
まぁ　確かにそう
自分でも思うわ　なんでこんなバカなことしたのかなぁって
why I would do something
as ridiculous as this.
Mm!
Riding your motorbike
to climb Mt. Fuji is silly.
バイクで富士山を登るなんて　バカみたい
Mm-hmm.
うん…
No way! I had no idea that your
Cub was the "Cursed Cub"!
まさか　あなたのカブがあの呪いのカブだったとはね！
You know about it?
知ってるの？
まっ　うわさくらいはね
Well, the stories, at least.
3 人殺したって言ってた…
It's said to have killed three people--
Ridiculous.
バカね
The old soba shop guy who first bought it
died from drinking too much.
最初に買ったソバ屋の爺さんは
カブとか関係なく　酒の飲みすぎでおっちんだのよ
It had nothing to do with the Cub.
The second guy, who ran a
bookstore, didn't even die;
2 代目の本屋のオヤジは　死んだんじゃなくって
he got into so much debt, he skipped town.
借金抱えて夜逃げだし
3 代目の神父は　単に免停で手放しただけ
And the third one was a priest who lost
his license, and parted ways with it.
Feel better now?
安心した？
Mm-hmm. But all three of them
sound like unsavory characters.
うん
けど　3 人ともロクでもないヤツみたい
じゃあ私そろそろ…
Well, I should get going.
Spend the night here.
泊まっていきなさい
えっ？
Huh?
ここら辺は街灯がないから　夜は真っ暗よ
There are no streetlights out here,
so it's pitch-black at night.
はい
Here!
やっぱり… バカなことしちゃったのかな
Maybe... it really was
a silly thing to do.
Mm-hmm. Silly.
うん… バカ
I can't believe you fell off partway up.
My Cub would have made it up to the top.
途中で落っこちるなんて
私のカブなら頂上まで登れてた
There's no way that would happen.
そんなことできるわけないじゃない
It's simply impossible to climb up
Mt. Fuji on a Cub. There's no way.
やっぱり　カブで富士山を登るなんて無理　不可能よ
It's silly, but I don't think it's
something that can't be done.
バカだけど　できないことはないと思う
Mm-hmm.
うん
It was August of 1963.
1963 年 8 月
A mountain climbing and bike enthusiast
who lived in Yamanashi Prefecture
スーパーカブは　山梨県在住の　登山　バイク愛好家によって
successfully climbed Mt. Fuji via
the Fujinomiya trail on a Super Cub.
富士宮口からの登頂に成功している
Then, that same year,
the curator of Ueno Zoo
更に同年
上野動物園の園長が　ハンターカブとモンキーの混成チームで
successfully made the climb up Mt. Fuji
using a composite team of
Hunter Cubs and Monkeys.
富士登山を達成した
And next, so will I.
次は　私も…
Here.
はい
Thanks.
ありがとう
What about the rest of your summer
vacation? We still have one week.
夏休み　どうする？
あと 1 週間
I'll fix up my Cub.
What do you have in mind?
カブを直す
あなたはどうするつもり？
I'm thinking of getting my license.
免許を取ろうと思う
免許って　自動二輪の？
Your license? A full motorcycle one?
Having just a Class I license is
holding me back in some ways.
原付一種のままじゃ　いろいろ不自由だし
I see. So that's what your job was about.
なるほど…
そのためのバイトか
Mm-hmm.
うん
I'm going to get a motorcycle license.
私は　バイクの免許を取る
よ～し　じゃあ早速予約を入れなくっちゃね
All right. Well, you'll need to make
a reservation right away.
Huh?
えっ…
ねぇ　予約って？
Wait, what reservation?
With a driving school, of course.
教習所に決まってるでしょ
エンジンの改造もしなくっちゃね
We'll have to soup up your engine, too.
There's no point in getting your license
and staying with a 50cc engine.
免許取っても　50cc のままじゃ意味ないし
お金がかかるのは困る
I can't handle anything too expensive.
Then how about modding your block?
ならブロック修正なんてどう？
Mod my block?
ブロック修正？
Yep.
そっ
You take the slight imperfections
in your engine block
エンジンブロックの燃焼室とか
シリンダーヘッドに発生する　鋳鉄特有のわずかな歪みを
specific to cast iron combustion
chambers and cylinder heads,
and, using equipment more precise
than what's on the production line,
メーカーの製造ラインよりも高精度な機材で　真円に削り直したあと
re-bore them out to be exactly circular,
then install oversized pistons to--
オーバーサイズピストンを使って…
Reiko!
礼子
Hmm?
んっ？
ごめん　ちょっとよくわかんない
Sorry, I'm not sure what you mean.
Gotcha. Okay, let me explain it
clearer from the beginning.
わかった　じゃあ最初からきっちり説明するわね
つまり　量産される…
You see, mass-produced engines are...
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"Super Cub Episode 6"
"My Cub"
第 6 話　「私のカブ」
"Super Cub Episode 6"
"My Cub"
Episode 6: "My Cub."